<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="druid-twilight.xml" url="https://github.com/Saerbhreathach/DAPC-aurora/blob/main/druid-twilight.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Circle of Twilight" type="Archetype" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_CIRCLEOFTWILIGHT">
		<supports>Druid Circle</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Circle of Twilight is an ancient sect of druids, long estranged from other druidic circles due to their differing outlooks on the natural world. The Circle of Twilight believes that the spirits of nature need regular sacrifices of beasts, natural and unnatural, and even the occasional human sacrifice. These druids meet in old, dying forests to perform secret blood rituals - rituals which they hope will appease the cruelest gods of the Old Faith. As a member of this circle, you realize nature’s will is not of kindness and spirituality - it is of cruelty and sacrifice.</p>
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUAL_SACRIFICE" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_LIFE_FROM_DEATH" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_EYES_OF_TWILIGHT" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_SOULSEEING" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUALIST" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>An ancient sect, Druids of the Circle of Twilight believe regular rituals of sacrifice will appease the cruelest of the Old Faith.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUAL_SACRIFICE" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_LIFE_FROM_DEATH" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_CIRCLE_SPELLS" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_EYES_OF_TWILIGHT" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_SOULSEEING" level="10" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUALIST" level="14" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Ritual Sacrifice" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUAL_SACRIFICE">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_RITUAL_SACRIFICE</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>When you choose this circle at 2nd level, you learn how to perform rituals using the blood sacrifices of powerful foes. By using the body of a creature that has died within the last 8 hours as one of your spell components, you can cast any spell with the ritual tag from any class spell list without needing to prepare it. The gentle repose spell cast on a body that’s been dead for less than 8 hours extends the duration that body may be used. You still need to use the other components of the ritual as normal.</p>
			<p class="indent">In order to cast a ritual in this manner, you need the body of a creature of a CR greater than or equal to the spell level of the ritual to be cast, and the spell must be of a level you have spell slots for. The creature used cannot be a construct, an undead, or an elemental. Once you complete the ritual, that creature cannot be used in any other rituals.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Use a body of CR greater or equal to the spell level to cast a spell of any class list as a ritual (must have spell slots of that level). You still need any other required components. The body must be dead less than 8 hours (can be extended by casting <i>gentle repose</i> on the corpse), and cannot be construct, undead or elemental. </description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Life From Death" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_LIFE_FROM_DEATH">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_LIFE_FROM_DEATH</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>Also at 2nd level, you can grasp the last breath of life energy from a falling creature, and use it to restore life to another. When a creature within 60 feet of you is reduced to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction and expend a spell slot to restore 1d8 hit points per level of the spell slot expended, adding your Wisdom modifier to the total, to yourself or another creature you can see within 60 feet. You cannot target the creature you reacted to.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="Reaction">
			<description>When a creature within 60 feet reaches 0 HP you can spend a spell slot. Give 1d8 (per slot level) + {{wisdom:modifier}} HP to yourself or another creature within 60 feet (cannot be the one with 0 HP).</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Circle Spells" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_CIRCLE_SPELLS">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_CIRCLE_SPELLS</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>The dark powers of twilight infuse you with the ability to cast certain spells. At 3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th level you gain access to a number of circle spells, listed below in the twilight table.</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you gain access to a circle spell, you always have it prepared, and it doesn’t count against the number of spells you can prepare each day. If you gain access to a spell that doesn’t appear on the druid spell list, the spell is nonetheless a druid spell for you.</p>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td>Druid Level</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td>3rd</td><td><em>darkness, gentle repose</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>5th</td><td><em>speak with dead, tides of blood†</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>7th</td><td><em>dominate beast, draining thread†</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>9th</td><td><em>dominate person, insect plague</em></td></tr>
			</table>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DARKNESS" level="3" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GENTLE_REPOSE" level="3" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SPEAK_WITH_DEAD" level="5" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_DAPC_SPELL_TIDES_OF_BLOOD" level="5" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DOMINATE_BEAST" level="7" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_DAPC_SPELL_DRAINING_THREAD" level="7" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DOMINATE_PERSON" level="9" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_INSECT_PLAGUE" level="9" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Eyes Of Twilight" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_EYES_OF_TWILIGHT">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_EYES_OF_TWILIGHT</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 6th level, you gain darkvision with a radius of 60 feet, or you increase the radius of your darkvision by 30 feet if you already have it. Additionally, you can see through magical darkness for the radius of your darkvision.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have darkvision up to {{darkvision:range}} feet. Your darkvision can see through magical darkness.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_LESSER_DARKVISION" />
			<stat name="darkvision:range" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<stat name="darkvision:range" value="30" bonus="eyes of twilight" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Soulseeing" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_SOULSEEING">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_TWILIGHT_SOULSEEING</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>At 10th level, you gain the ability to see the souls of living creatures. As an action on your turn, you hone your senses to allow you to see the outline of any living creature or creature that has died within the last 8 hours. This allows you to see any creature within the radius of your darkvision, including invisible creatures, as well as creatures that are obscured in some manner, such as being behind a wall or in murky water. This sight can penetrate most barriers, but it is blocked by 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt. This sight can be maintained for up to 10 minutes by using your action each turn. If your turn ends and you haven’t used your action to maintain this feature, it ends early.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use this feature twice. You regain expended uses when you finish a short or long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action" usage="2/Short or Long Rest">
			<description>You can see the outline of a creature, living or dead within the last 8 hours, within {{darkvision:range}} feet. This includes invisible and obscured creatures. This sight is blocked by 3 feet of wood or dirt, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, or a thin sheet of lead. This vision continues for up to 10 minutes as long as you maintain it with an action each turn.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Thousand Forms" type="Archetype Feature" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_WOTC_PHB_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CIRCLE_MOON_THOUSAND_FORMS">
		<requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_THOUSAND_FORMS</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>By 14th level, you have learned to use magic to alter your physical form in more subtle ways. You can cast the alter self spell at will.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can cast the alter self spell at will.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ALTER_SELF" spellcasting="Druid" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Feature Replacement Grants-->
	<element name="Combat Wild Shape Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_COMBAT_WILD_SHAPE" />
	<element name="Circle Forms Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_CIRCLE_FORMS" />
	<element name="Primal Strike Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_PRIMAL_STRIKE" />
	<element name="Elemental Wild Shape Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_ELEMENTAL_WILD_SHAPE" />
	<element name="Thousand Forms Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_DRUID_CIRCLE_MOON_THOUSAND_FORMS" />
</elements>
