<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Shadar-kai</name>
		<description></description>
		<author url="https://www.reddit.com/r/UnearthedArcana/comments/c1otzd/dark_arts_players_companion_v30_53_pages_of_races/">Jonoman3000</author>
		<update version="3.0">
			<file name="race-shadar-kai.xml" url="https://github.com/Saerbhreathach/DAPC-aurora/blob/main/race-shadar-kai.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
	<element name="Shadar-kai" type="Race" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_HOMEBREW_DAPC_RACE_SHADAR_KAI">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">Shadar-kai were once humans, native to the world. They were all members of an extended tribe who called themselves Shadar-Kai. These early humans had 
            seen the abuses Nerull, once god of death, perpetrated on the souls who passed into his power. They also feared the unknowable reaches of death into which most souls 
            pass even now. When the Raven Queen slew Nerull and ascended to godhood, in an age now largely forgotten, the Shadar-Kai struck a deal with her. They promised to serve 
            as her mortal agents, and in exchange, she gave them incredibly long life and freedom from frailty. The Shadar-kai believe that, through their pact, they became the 
            chosen people of death and winter.</p>
            <p class="indent">The Shadar-Kai moved to the Shadowfell, setting up their communities on the borders of Letherna, the Raven Queen’s domain. Life in shadow changed the 
            humans, reshaping them and altering their appearance. Eventually, they were so different from humans that they became a distinct species. As they expanded their territory 
            in the Shadowfell and began interacting again with the mortal world, the tribal name became the name for their race.</p>
			<h4>ASHEN AND SCARRED</h4>
			<p>Shadar-kai are humanlike, but the weight of existence in the Shadowfell has shaped them to be slightly shorter and much thinner than their human counterparts. A 
            Shadar-kai has a colorless complexion that varies from alabaster to dark gray. Shadar-kai hair is similarly drab or raven black. Pale hair might have a hint of color 
            within the range of human norms. The eyes are lustrous and black, lacking any white or clear pupil. Shadows near a Shadar-kai sometimes seem to reach out or deepen, 
            especially when the Shadar-kai is angry.</p>
			<p class="indent">Although drab in natural appearance, Shadar-kai are quite elaborate and idiosyncratic in personal adornment. They like dark and exotic clothing, 
            jewelry, and weapons, often decorated with swatches of bright color. Hair is similarly ornate and often dyed, and many embellish their skin with tattoos, scars, and 
            piercings.</p>
			<p class="indent">The tattoos, scars, and piercings a Shadar-kai wears have more than one purpose. They exist as a testament to the wearer’s ability to withstand pain as 
            well as a means of personal expression and decoration. Each decoration can also be a record of a deed done, an honor gained, or a misdeed declared.</p>
			<h4>THE RAVEN QUEEN</h4>
			<p>Through their pact with the Raven Queen, each Shadar-kai is an instrument of death and fate. The Raven Queen doesn’t demand worship from the Shadar-kai, though she 
            receives it in abundance. She demands only that they observe the pact by following her commandments. So most Shadar-kai hold no pity for the dying and try to punish those 
            who defy fate. But Shadar-kai also believe that nobody truly knows what fate holds.</p>
			<p class="indent">The Raven Queen is a fair mother, if not a loving one. When the Shadar-kai called upon her in ancient times, she answered. She still does. While she 
            spares little love, she also never demands the love of her children. Almost all Shadar-kai revere the Raven Queen, but each Shadar-kai is free to choose his or her 
            destiny and way of life, including religion.</p>
            <div class="reference">
				<div name="The Raven Queen" id="ID_HOMEBREW_DAPC_DEITY_THE_RAVEN_QUEEN">
                    <p><i>Goddess of Death, Fate &amp; Winter</i></p>
                    <p>
                        <span class="feature">Alignment:</span>Unaligned<br />
                    <span class="feature">Suggested Domains</span>Death, Nature.<br />
                        <span class="feature">Symbol</span>Head of a black raven<br />
                    </p>
                    <p>The Raven Queen was once a powerful mortal sorcerer-queen. When she died, she came to Pluton, the domain of the evil death god Nerull. Nerull, impressed with her 
                    will and ambition, gave her form and made her his consort, naming her Nera. She stole Nerull's power over mortal shades, and by freeing most of them she managed to 
                    destroy Nerull and become the god of death.</p>
                    <p class="indent">After overthrowing Nerull, she abandoned Pluton and created her own realm in the Shadowfell.</p>
                    <p class="indent">She is the spinner of fate and the patron of winter. She marks the end of each mortal life, and mourners call upon her during funeral rites, in the 
                    hope that she will guard the departed from the curse of undeath. She expects her followers to abide by these commandments:</p>
                    <p>1. Hold no pity for those who suffer and die, for death is the natural end of life.</p>
                    <p>2. Bring down the proud who try to cast off the chains of fate; you must punish hubris where you find it.</p>
                    <p>3. Destroy the cults of Orcus, for the Demon Prince of the Undead seeks to claim the Raven Queen's throne.</p>
            </div>
			<h4>STRONG EMOTIONS</h4>
			<p>The Shadowfell saps living creatures of creativity and the will to live. When shadar-kai moved to the Shadowfell ages ago, they were not immune to this depression. 
            Numerous members of their early society gave in to ennui and simply slipped out of existence, driving the Shadar-kai to change their lifestyle, embracing strong emotions 
            and peak experiences. These practices, born out of necessity, became traditions over countless generations.</p>
			<p class="indent">The current culture of the Shadar-kai is a study in pushing boundaries. Shadar-kai welcome difficult tasks and physical and emotional extremes as a way 
            of life. They learn to channel the darkness of the Shadowfell rather than allowing that darkness to consume them. And they accept death as the inevitable end for those 
            who fail to attain the right amount of power or fame.</p>
			<p class="indent">Shadar-kai embrace living with gusto. The limits of pleasure and pain distract them from the wearying melancholy of the Shadowfell. They also strive for 
            personal greatness, so that if they fail to gain the ability to live forever, stories of their great deeds will grant a sort of immortality. In this search for personal 
            glory, most Shadar-kai ignore banalities such as comfort and safety.</p>
			<h4>CALL OF THE SHADOWFELL</h4>
			<p>Although Shadar-kai leave the Shadowfell to seek fortune in the world and among the planes, a few needs and wants drive a Shadar-kai to return home from time to time. 
            Most Shadar-kai feel a basic need to visit the enveloping dimness of the Shadowfell at least intermittently. The plane is unlike even the darkest reaches of other planes. 
            Obtaining new adornments and equipment in the proper style often requires a return to the Shadowfell. Shadar-kai also return to their gloomy settlements to spend time 
            among those who see extreme, weird, or even deviant as normal. And they come home to brag.</p>
            <h4>SHADAR-KAI NAMES</h4>
            <p>Shadar-kai have similar names to their human counterparts, though they did change slightly due to their isolation in the Shadowfell, with the only real influencing 
            force being the will of the Raven Queen. Their names are often merely the inventions of their parents, though some common names do exist.</p>
			<p>
                <span class="feature">Male Names:</span>Albrek, Baden, Codren, Emul, Horiam, Hutahn, Ioan, Lucyan, Mahahn, Niku, Ovid, Petru, Razvahn, Serbahn, Shathys, Teodahr, 
                Vasylay, Zahar.<br />
                <span class="feature">Female Names:</span>Afyn, Anka, Bahnka, Codruta, Doru, Dyon, Floahr, Ghita, Helayna, Ioana, Jenit, Katryn, Lucya, Markella, Nadya, Roduka, 
                Sahyeh, Tabita, Yalda, Zyna<br />
			</p>
			<h4>SHADAR-KAI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>The weight of existence in the Shadowfell has shaped the physical qualities of the Shadar-kai, granting them traits unique to their native realm.<br />
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Dexterity score increases by 2 and either your Intelligence score or your Charisma score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Age.</span>The Shadar-kai reach physical maturity at the same rate as humans, but they generally live far longer. A Shadar-kai may live up to 
                800 years.<br />
				<span class="feature">Alignment.</span>Shadar-kai society is often seen as cruel and apathetic. The Shadar-kai generally strive to create chaos and death, bringing 
                death for both purposes of evil as well as good.<br />
				<span class="feature">Size.</span>Shadar-kai are generally a tad below 6 feet in height and they weigh between 110 and 170 pounds. Your size is medium.<br />
				<span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.<br />        
				<span class="feature">Superior Darkvision.</span>Accustomed to the black skies and eternal shadow of the Shadowfell, you have superior vision in dark and dim 
                conditions. You can see in dim light within 120 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, 
                only shades of grey.<br />
				<span class="feature">Celestial Resistance.</span>You have resistance to necrotic damage and radiant damage.<br />
				<span class="feature">Healing Hands.</span>As an action, you can touch a creature and cause it to regain a number of hit points equal to your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
				<span class="feature">Light Bearer.</span>You know the light cantrip. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it.<br />
				<span class="feature">Languages.</span>You can speak, read, and write Common and Celestial.<br />      
				<span class="feature">Subrace.</span>Three subraces of aasimar exist: protector aasimar, scourge aasimar, and fallen aasimar. Choose one of them for your character.<br />
			</p>     
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Albrek, Baden, Codren, Emul, Horiam, Hutahn, Ioan, Lucyan, Mahahn, Niku, Ovid, Petru, Razvahn, Serbahn, Shathys, Teodahr, Vasylay, Zahar.</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Afyn, Anka, Bahnka, Codruta, Doru, Dyon, Floahr, Ghita, Helayna, Ioana, Jenit, Katryn, Lucya, Markella, Nadya, Roduka, Sahyeh, Tabita, 
            Yalda, Zyna</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}}</set>
            <set name="height" modifier="1d10">5'6"</set>
            <set name="weight" modifier="2d4">100 lb.</set>   
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="charisma" value="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_CELESTIAL" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Customized Language" supports="Custom Race Language" number="2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_AASIMAR_SUBRACE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Celestial Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You have resistance to necrotic damage and radiant damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have resistance to necrotic damage and radiant damage.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_NECROTIC" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_RADIANT" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Healing Hands" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS">
		<description>
			<p>As an action, you can touch a creature and cause it to regain a number of hit points equal to your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You can touch a creature and cause it to regain {{trait:healing-hands}} hit points.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="trait:healing-hands" value="level" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Light Bearer" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER">
		<description>
			<p>You know the light cantrip. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the light cantrip. (Spellcasting: Charisma)</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_LIGHT" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Aasimar Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_AASIMAR_SUBRACE">
		<description>
			<p>Three subraces of aasimar exist: protector aasimar, scourge aasimar, and fallen aasimar. Choose one of them for your character.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Aasimar Subrace" supports="Aasimar" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Protector Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_PROTECTOR_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Protector aasimar are charged by the powers of good to guard the weak, to strike at evil wherever it arises, and to stand vigilant against the darkness. From a young age, a protector aasimar receives advice and directives that urge to stand against evil.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Wisdom score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Radiant Soul.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to glimmer and two luminous, incorporeal wings to sprout from your back. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>  
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Protector Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_SOUL" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Radiant Soul" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_SOUL">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to glimmer and two luminous, incorporeal wings to sprout from your back.</p>
			<p>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level.</p>
			<p>Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Scourge Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_Scourge_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Scourge aasimar are imbued with a divine energy that blazes intensely within them. It feeds a powerful desire to destroy evil-a desire that is, at its best, unflinching and, at its worst, all-consuming. Many scourge aasimar wear masks to block out the world and focus on containing this power, unmasking themselves only in battle.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Constitution score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Radiant Consumption.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing a searing light to radiate from you, pour out of your eyes and mouth, and threaten to char you. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take radiant damage equal to half your level (rounded up). In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Scourge Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_CONSUMPTION" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Radiant Consumption" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_CONSUMPTION">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing a searing light to radiate from you, pour out of your eyes and mouth, and threaten to char you.</p>
			<p>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take radiant damage equal to half your level (rounded up). In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level.</p>
			<p>Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take {{level:half:up}} radiant damage. In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Fallen Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_FALLEN_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>An aasimar who was touched by dark powers as a youth or who turns to evil in early adulthood can become one of the fallen-a group of aasimar whose inner light has been replaced by shadow.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Strength score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Necrotic Shroud.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to turn into pools of darkness and two skeletal, ghostly, flightless wings to sprout from your back. The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra necrotic damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="strength" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Fallen Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_NECROTIC_SHROUD" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Necrotic Shroud" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_NECROTIC_SHROUD">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to turn into pools of darkness and two skeletal, ghostly, flightless wings to sprout from your back. The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</p>
			<p class="indent">Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra necrotic damage equals your level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC {{necrotic shroud:dc}}) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="8" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="proficiency" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="charisma:modifier" />
		</rules>
	</element>
</elements>
