<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Wight</name>
		<update version="3.0">
			<file name="race-wight.xml" url="https://github.com/Saerbhreathach/DAPC-aurora/blob/main/race-wight.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Wight" type="Race" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_HOMEBREW_DAPC_RACE_WIGHT">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">The word "wight" meant "person" in days of yore, but the name now refers to evil undead who were once mortals driven by dark desire and great vanity. 
			When death stills such a creature's heart and snuffs its living breath, its spirit cries out to the demon lord Orcus or some vile god of the underworld for a reprieve: 
			undeath in return for eternal war on the living. If a dark power answers the call, the spirit is granted undeath so that it can pursue its own malevolent agenda.</p>
			<p class="indent">Wights possess the memories and drives of their formerly living selves. They will heed the call of whatever dark entity transformed them into undead, 
			swearing oaths to appease their new lord while retaining their autonomy. Never tiring, a wight can pursue its goals relentlessly and without distraction.</p>
			<h4>LIFE EATERS</h4>
			<p>Neither dead nor alive, a wight exists in a transitional state between one world and the next. The bright spark it possessed in life is gone, and in its place is a 
			yearning to consume that spark in all living things. When a wight attacks, this life essence glows like white-hot embers to its dark eyes, and the wight's cold touch can 
			drain the spark through flesh, clothing, and armor.</p>
			<h4>SHADOW OF THE GRAVE</h4>
			<p>Wights flee from the world by day, away from the light of the sun, which they hate. They retreat to barrow mounds, crypts, and tombs where they dwell. Their lairs are 
			silent, desolate places, surrounded by dead plants, noticeably blackened, and avoided by bird and beast.</p>
			<p class="indent">Humanoids slain by a wight can rise as zombies under its control. Motivated by hunger for living souls and driven by the same desire for power that 
			awakened them in undeath, some wights serve as shock troops for evil leaders, including wraiths. As soldiers, they are able to plan but seldom do so, relying on their 
			hunger for destruction to overwhelm any creature that stands before them.</p>
			<h4>WIGHT NAMES</h4>
			<p>When they are created, a wight keeps all of the memories of its former life, and therefore keeps its name as well. Therefore, wights can have all types of names based 
			on whatever race they were in life.</p>
			<h4>AWIGHT TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your wight character has certain traits derived from its undead nature.<br />
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Constitution score increases by 2 and your Charisma score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Age.</span>As beings of undeath, Wights do not age or mature, and can live for thousands of years if they are not killed in battle.<br />
				<span class="feature">Alignment.</span>Wights are transformed by dark entities to serve their needs, and therefore are most often evil themselves. Although they 
				retain their memories and personalities, Wights are only created from evil and vain humans, so they will remain evil unless they change their alignment after reaching 
				undeath.<br />
				<span class="feature">Size.</span>Wights are between 5 and 6 feet tall and average about 180 pounds. Your size is medium.<br />
				<span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.<br />        
				<span class="feature">Dark Vision.</span>As a being forced to live in darkness, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 
				60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of grey.<br />
				<span class="feature">Life Drain.</span>When you kill a humanoid, you can choose to have it rise 24 hours later as a zombie under your control, unless it is restored 
				to life or its body is destroyed. Only one zombie may be created through this ability at any one time; if another is created then the first becomes inanimate. The 
				zombie has the statistics of the Zombie (Monster Manual pg. 316), except its hp value is instead equal to three times your level.<br />
				<span class="feature">Sunlight Sensitivity.</span>You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of 
				your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.<br />
				<span class="feature">Undead.</span>Your type is both humanoid and undead, meaning you are affected by any features or abilities that affect either of those types. 
				For example, you can be targeted by <i>hold person</i> or turned by <i>turn undead</i>. The exception to this is healing: any spell, feature, or ability that restores hit points 
				and normally has no effect on undead instead restores you for half the number of hit points it would normally restore, rather than having no effect. Due to your 
				undead nature, you are immune to disease and the poisoned condition, and you have resistance to poison damage. You do not need to eat or breathe, but you can ingest 
				food or drink if you wish. Instead of sleeping, you enter an inactive state for 4 hours each day. You do not dream in this state, but resting in this way is otherwise 
				identical to sleeping. Magically induced sleep can cause you to enter this inactive state.<br />
				<span class="feature">Languages.</span>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language you knew in life.<br />
			</p>        
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="charisma" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Mummy)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Mummy)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="25" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Customized Language" supports="Standard||Exotic" number="2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Extra Language (Mummy)" supports="Standard||Exotic" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_AASIMAR_SUBRACE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Celestial Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You have resistance to necrotic damage and radiant damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have resistance to necrotic damage and radiant damage.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_NECROTIC" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_RADIANT" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Healing Hands" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS">
		<description>
			<p>As an action, you can touch a creature and cause it to regain a number of hit points equal to your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You can touch a creature and cause it to regain {{trait:healing-hands}} hit points.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="trait:healing-hands" value="level" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Light Bearer" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER">
		<description>
			<p>You know the light cantrip. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the light cantrip. (Spellcasting: Charisma)</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_LIGHT" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Aasimar Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_AASIMAR_SUBRACE">
		<description>
			<p>Three subraces of aasimar exist: protector aasimar, scourge aasimar, and fallen aasimar. Choose one of them for your character.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Aasimar Subrace" supports="Aasimar" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Protector Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_PROTECTOR_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Protector aasimar are charged by the powers of good to guard the weak, to strike at evil wherever it arises, and to stand vigilant against the darkness. From a young age, a protector aasimar receives advice and directives that urge to stand against evil.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Wisdom score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Radiant Soul.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to glimmer and two luminous, incorporeal wings to sprout from your back. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>  
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Protector Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_SOUL" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Radiant Soul" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_SOUL">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to glimmer and two luminous, incorporeal wings to sprout from your back.</p>
			<p>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level.</p>
			<p>Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you have a flying speed of 30 feet, and once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Scourge Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_Scourge_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Scourge aasimar are imbued with a divine energy that blazes intensely within them. It feeds a powerful desire to destroy evil-a desire that is, at its best, unflinching and, at its worst, all-consuming. Many scourge aasimar wear masks to block out the world and focus on containing this power, unmasking themselves only in battle.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Constitution score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Radiant Consumption.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing a searing light to radiate from you, pour out of your eyes and mouth, and threaten to char you. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take radiant damage equal to half your level (rounded up). In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Scourge Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_CONSUMPTION" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Radiant Consumption" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_RADIANT_CONSUMPTION">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing a searing light to radiate from you, pour out of your eyes and mouth, and threaten to char you.</p>
			<p>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take radiant damage equal to half your level (rounded up). In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra radiant damage equals your level.</p>
			<p>Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, and at the end of each of your turns, you and each creature within 10 feet of you take {{level:half:up}} radiant damage. In addition, once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Fallen Aasimar" type="Sub Race" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_WOTC_VGTM_SUB_RACE_FALLEN_AASIMAR">
		<supports>Aasimar</supports>
		<description>
			<p>An aasimar who was touched by dark powers as a youth or who turns to evil in early adulthood can become one of the fallen-a group of aasimar whose inner light has been replaced by shadow.</p>
			<p>     
				<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Strength score increases by 1.<br />
				<span class="feature">Necrotic Shroud.</span>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to turn into pools of darkness and two skeletal, ghostly, flightless wings to sprout from your back. The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra necrotic damage equals your level. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.<br />
			</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<stat name="strength" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Fallen Aasimar)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_NECROTIC_SHROUD" level="3" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Necrotic Shroud" type="Racial Trait" source="Volo’s Guide to Monsters" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_AASIMAR_NECROTIC_SHROUD">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your action to unleash the divine energy within yourself, causing your eyes to turn into pools of darkness and two skeletal, ghostly, flightless wings to sprout from your back. The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</p>
			<p class="indent">Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra necrotic damage equals your level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>The instant you transform, other creatures within 10 feet of you that can see you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC {{necrotic shroud:dc}}) or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it as a bonus action. During it, once on each of your turns, you can deal {{level}} extra necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="8" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="proficiency" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="charisma:modifier" />
		</rules>
	</element>
</elements>
