<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Deathtouched Sorcerous Origin</name>
		<description>The Deathtouched Sorcerous Origin from Dark Arts Player's Companion</description>
		<author url="https://www.reddit.com/r/UnearthedArcana/comments/c1otzd/dark_arts_players_companion_v30_53_pages_of_races/">Jonoman3000</author>
		<update version="3.0">
			<file name="sorcerer-deathtouched.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Saerbhreathach/DAPC-aurora/main/sorcerer-deathtouched.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Deathtouched" type="Archetype" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_SORCERER_ARCHETYPE_DEATHTOUCHED">
		<supports>Sorcerous Origin</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your innate magic comes from a past encounter with death. Most often, this origin is traced back to surviving an attack from an undead, such as a vampire’s bite, a ghost’s possession, or a specter’s life drain. Or, it could have originated from an imperfect revival or near-death experience. Regardless of the way you attained this dark magic, it now dictates your life and greatly augments your power.</p>
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_GHOSTLY_BODY" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_MEMORIES_OF_THE_FALLEN" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_NECROTIC_AFFINITY" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_INCORPOREAL_FIGURE" />
			<div element="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_POSSESSION" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_GHOSTLY_BODY" level="1" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_MEMORIES_OF_THE_FALLEN" level="1" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_NECROTIC_AFFINITY" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_INCORPOREAL_FIGURE" level="14" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_POSSESSION" level="18" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Ghostly Body" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_GHOSTLY_BODY">
		<description>
			<p>Starting when you choose this origin at 1st level, your body becomes imbued with dark power. Your hit point maximum is increased by 1, and increases by 1 again whenever you gain a level in this class.</p>
			<p class="indent">Additionally, this power allows your body to slowly fade into invisibility. If you remain still for 1 minute while in dim light or darkness, you become invisible until you move, enter bright light, or use an action, bonus action, or reaction.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you reach 3rd level in this class, you can use your bonus action and spend 1 sorcery point to activate this feature without waiting a minute, causing you to immediately become invisible.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can spend 1 minute standing still to become invisible in dim light or darkness. The effect ends when you move, enter bright light, use an action, bonus action, or reaction.</description>
			<description level="3">You can spend your bonus action and 1 sorcery point to become invisible in dim light or darkness. The effect ends when you move, enter bright light, use an action, bonus action, or reaction.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="hp" value="level"/>
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Memories of the Fallen" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_MEMORIES_OF_THE_FALLEN">
		<description>
			<p>Also at 1st level, you gain the ability to access the memories of the deceased. By performing a 1 minute ritual on a corpse, you can gain insight into how that creature died. If you already witnessed that creature’s death, you instead gain another random memory from that creature, as determined by your DM. This feature can only be used once per corpse.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You perform a ritual for 1-minute on a corpse and gain insight into how it died. If you witnessed its death, your DM will provide another random memory. This ability can only be used once per corpse.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Necrotic Affinity" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_NECROTIC_AFFINITY">
		<description>
			<p>At 6th level, you learn two Necromancy spells from any class. A spell you choose must be of a level you can cast. Whenever you gain a level in this class, you may choose one of these Necromancy spells and replace it with another Necromancy spell from any class. The chosen spells count as sorcerer spells for you but don’t count against the number of sorcerer spells you know.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Spell" name="Necrotic Affinity" supports="(0||$(spellcasting:slots)),Necromancy" number="2" level="6" spellcasting="Sorcerer" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Incorporeal Figure" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_INCORPOREAL_FIGURE">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 14th level, you have the ability to become temporarily incorporeal. As a bonus action on your turn, you can spend 2 sorcery points to become incorporeal, gaining the ability to move through objects as if the objects were difficult terrain, and you become immune to the grappled and restrained conditions. For the duration, your movement doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks, and your speed is increased by 15 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent">The incorporeal effect ends at the end of your next turn. If you are inside an object when the effect ends, you are ejected to the nearest empty space and take 1d10 force damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action">
			<description>You spend 2 sorcery points and become incorporeal - for the duration of your turn, you can move through objects as difficult terrain, are immune to being grappled or restrained, do not provoke opportunity attacks, and your speed increases 15 feet. If you are inside an object when the effect ends, you ar ejected into the nearest empty space and take 1d10 force damage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Possession" type="Archetype Feature" source="Dark Arts Player's Companion" id="ID_JONOMAN3000_DAPC_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_DEATHTOUCHED_POSSESSION">
		<description>
			<p>At 18th level, you gain the ability to take control of another creature’s body. As an action, you can spend 5 sorcery points to attempt to possess a creature of size Large or smaller within 5 feet of you. That creature must succeed on a Charisma saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC or be possessed for up to 1 hour. On a success, you then disappear, and the target is incapacitated and loses control of its body. While possessing a creature, you can't be targeted by any attack, spell, or other effect, and you retain your alignment, Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma. You otherwise use the possessed target's statistics, but don’t gain access to the target's knowledge, class features, or proficiencies.</p>
			<p class="indent">At the start of each of your turns, if the possessed creature has been damaged at least once since the end of your last turn it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on a success. You may also end the effect using your bonus action. A target is immune to Possession for 24 hours after succeeding on the saving throw.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You can spend 5 sorcery points to attempt to possess a Large or smaller creature within 5 feet. The creature must succeed on a DC {{spell-save:dc}} Charisma saving throw or be possessed for 1 hour. You disappear and the target is incapacitated. While possessing a creature, you can't be targeted by any attack, spell or effect. You retain your alignment, Intelligence, Wisdom and Charisma, but take on the target's other stats. You don't receive their knowledge, class features or proficiencies.&#13;At the start of your turn, if the possessed creature has taken damage, it can repeat the saving throw. The effect ends on a success. You can end it with your bonus action. A target is immune to possession for 24 hours after succeeding on its saving throw.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="spell-save:dc" value="8"/>
			<stat name="spell-save:dc" value="proficiency"/>
			<stat name="spell-save:dc" value="charisma"/>
		</rules>
	</element>
</elements>
